[音乐]
[MUSIC]
&gt；&gt；Kyle：我想教你的最后一个模式是。
&gt;&gt; Kyle: The last pattern that I want to teach you is.
顺便说一下，在我教完最后一个模式之后，还有最后一个练习。
And by the way, after I teach of this last pattern there's a last exercise.
所以我将在练习9中教你CSP。
So I'm gonna teach you CSP in exercise nine.
练习10是我构建的一个更复杂的应用程序，
Exercise ten is a much more sophisticated application that I've built,
它被称为三个名单的故事。
it's called a tale of three list.
而你在那里的练习将会回到过去，重新审视反应性或
And your exercise there is going to be to go back and revisit either reactive or
CSP在一个更复杂的应用程序的上下文中。
CSP in the context of a much more sophisticated application.
所以，如果你想在这方面多加练习，那就是练习十。
So if you're looking for more practice on that stuff, it's coming with exercise ten.
所以不要觉得这是我们最后一次谈论它。
So don't feel like that's the last that we're gonna talk about it.
但我想换个角度
But I want to shift gears and
重点介绍我们要介绍的最后一个主要模式，称为CSP。
focus on our last major pattern to introduce is called CSP.
CSP是关于与通道的并发性建模的。
CSP is about modeling concurrency with channels.
我们现在已经以三种、四种或五种不同的方式对并发进行了建模。
We've modeled concurrency now three, or four, or five different ways.
这是建模并发性的另一种方法。
This is another way of modeling concurrency.
还有渠道，如果你想知道什么是渠道，
And channels, if you wanna think about what is a channel,
渠道有点像小溪，有点像管道。
a channel is kinda like a stream, it's kinda like a pipe.
除了有一个重要的特征
Except there's one important characteristic and
也就是说，管道没有缓冲区大小，并且
that is that the pipe has no buffer size and
因此，它自动地内置了背压的概念。
therefore has automatically built into it this notion of back pressure.
因此，如果您在听说或之前已经进行过流空间编程
So if you've done stream space programming before you've probably heard or
阅读关于背压的概念。
read about this notion of back pressure.
但为了说明这一点，我想让你们想象一下，我有两个
But to illustrate that I want you to imagine that I have two
软管的不同末端。
different ends of a hose.
这边走一条路，然后这边走一条路，然后
One way over here and then one way over here, and
两端都有两个人。
there's two people on either end.
他们彼此看不见，彼此之间没有任何交流。
And they don't see each other, they don't have any communication between each other.
然后这边的人说我要开始
And then this guy on this side says I'm gonna start
通过软管往下倒一些水。
pouring some water down through the hose.
另一端的人让水出来，他正在喷水。
And the guy on the other end has the water coming out and he's spraying it.
在某个时候，喷水的人说我不想要更多的水了。
At some point the guy who's spraying the water says I don't want any more water.
但他和这个人没有联系，
But he doesn't have a communication with this guy,
那他怎么跟这家伙说我不想再喝水了？
so how is he going to tell this guy I don't want any more water?
他会把软管盖上以便在另一端
Well he's gonna cap off the hose so that on the other end
没有更多的水可以进去，因为软管已经完全充满了。
no more water can go in because the hose is completely filled up.
那是背压。
That's back pressure.
这是一种相反的沟通方式
That's a reverse way of communicating up
从消费者到生产者说停止生产，因为我不想再要了。
from consumer to producer to say stop producing cuz I don't want any more.
大家都在跟踪我吗？
Is everybody following me?
这就像是5万英尺高的东西。
This is like 50,000 foot view of stuff.
嗯，在我们的应用程序中有一些地方我们
Well there are places in our applications where we
生产者和消费者之间没有直接联系。
don't have a direct connection between producer and consumer.
因为我们故意把它们分开。
Because we've intentionally kept them separate.
但我们确实希望有一个信号，某种方式向制作人发出信号。
But we do want to have a signal, some way of signaling to the producer.
我不想在这一端接受更多的数据，停止给我发东西。
I don't wanna take any more data on this end, stop sending me stuff.
在RxJS的世界里，这就是他们对热和冷可观测的区别，
In the RxJS world that's their distinction between hot and cold observables,
顺便说一下。
by the way.
但是在冷热观测值之间的转换并不是那么干净和
But converting between hot and cold observables is not quite as clean and
很容易，至少在我的实践中，就像理论上看起来的那样。
easy, at least in my practice, as it might seem in theory.
因此，建模该信号的另一种方法是使用CSP系统中的信道。
So another way of modeling that signal is to use a channel in a CSP system.
因为频道，就像我说的，
Because the channel, as I said,
就像一个管道，一次只能接收一条消息。
is like a pipe that can only take one message at a time.
它会自动产生背压，
And it automatically has back pressure,
这意味着在我准备好之前你不能给我寄东西。
and what that means is you can't send me something until I'm ready to take it.
在你准备好发送之前我不能拿东西。
And I can't take something until you're ready to send it.
大家都在跟踪我吗？
Is everybody following me?
那里没有排队。
There's no queue there.
这是通过通道传输的一条消息。
It's one message that transfers through the channel.
所以，这就是阻塞通道的概念。
So, it's this notion of blocking channels.
现在是CSP，它代表通信顺序进程。
Now CSP, it stands for communicating sequential processes.
这实际上是60年代发明的一种模式。
This actually was a pattern invented way back in the 60s.
一个叫Hoare的家伙，他写了一本书叫做“交流顺序过程”。
Guy named Hoare, he wrote this book called Communicating Sequential Processes.
这是一个管理并发的模型。
It was a model for managing concurrency.
你们中的一些人可能听说过并发的参与者模型，
Some of you may have heard of the actor model of concurrency,
两者之间存在着密切但不直接的关系。
and there's a close but not direct relationship between the two.
与演员的主要区别，至少从我的研究来看，主要区别是
The major difference with actors, at least from my research, the major difference
和演员对这件事，我马上要跟你谈的。
with actors versus this thing that I'm about to talk to you about.
对于参与者，当您发送消息时，它是异步的。
With actors when you send a message it's asynchronous.
你发送一条信息
You send a message and
在另一个点上，另一端的某个人拿起了它。
at some other point, somebody on the other end picks it up.
使用CSP，当您发送消息时，它是非常同步的。
With CSP when you send a message it's very synchronous.
至少语义是，它是非常同步的。
At least the semantics are, it's very synchronous.
当我想要传递信息的时候，必须有人在另一端
When I wanna send a message there has to be somebody on the other end that's
准备好了。
ready to take it.
因为我的软管一次只能接受一条信息，好吧。
Cuz my hose can only accept one message at a time, okay.
如果你听说过演员的话，这就是主要的区别。
So that's the major difference if you've heard about actors.
这是使用CSP进行同步消息传递的主要区别
It's the major difference between synchronous message passing with CSP
与使用参与者的异步消息传递相反。
versus asynchronous message passing with actors.
那么，通信顺序进程，这是关于什么的呢？
So communicating sequential processes, what is what does this all about?
它是关于用大量的Tiny对您的应用程序进行建模的
It's about modeling your application with lots of tiny
我们称之为流程的独立部分。
independent pieces that we call processes.
如果JavaScript有完整的&gt；&gt；Kyle：就像线程一样，
And if JavaScript had full &gt;&gt; Kyle: like threading to it,
如果我们可以像您在Node中做的那样，您可以在其中设置子流程和其他东西。
if we could do like you can in Node where you can set up child processes and stuff.
如果我们有完整的线程，那么每个独立的部分都将在它的
If we had full threading then every independent piece would be on its
自己的线程，它将完全独立于其他人运行。
own thread and it would be running entirely independently of everybody else.
这很好，因为很多时候他们都在做自己的事情。
Well that's great because a lot of the times they are doing their own thing.
但在某些情况下，这两个独立的部分
But there are cases where these two independent pieces
需要相互协调。
need to coordinate with each other.
因此，您的应用程序有两个不同的部分，它们通常只是
So you have two different parts of your application that are normally just kind of
奔跑做自己的事情。
running doing their own thing.
但有一种状态，他们会说我需要沟通
But there is a state in which they get to where they say I need to communicate
和这个人在一起。
with this guy.
这个家伙到达了一个他说我需要那个家伙的一些信息的州。
And this guy gets to a state where he says I need some information from that guy.
所以不管他们独立做了什么，
So whatever they've been doing independently,
他们到了说我们需要协调的地步。
they get to a point where they say we need to coordinate.
并且以这种方式在任一方向上发送消息，或者可能在两个方向上都发送消息，一个消息，
And send a message in either direction, or perhaps both, one message this way,
回一条信息。
one message back.
然后一旦消息通过，它们就会变得畅通无阻
And then as soon as the messages have passed, they become unblocked and
他们回到了独立的状态。
they go back to being independent.
这就是我们所说的过程，
That's what we mean by processes,
理论上这些东西可以独立运行。
is that these things could in theory run independently.
现在我们知道在JavaScript中，
Now we know within JavaScript,
事情并不是像那样独立运行的。
things aren't actually running independently like that.
但我们今天看到了一些类似的行为。
But we have seen something today that does sort of act like that.
有人知道我在说什么吗？&gt；&gt；Kyle：没有
Does anybody know what I'm talking about? &gt;&gt; Kyle: Didn't
我们今天看到的一些东西，像它这样的行为可以阻止自己，而不是
we see something today that sort of acts like it can just block itself and not
影响任何其他应用程序？&gt；&gt；扬声器2：[听不到]
affect any of the rest of the application? &gt;&gt; Speaker 2: [INAUDIBLE]
&gt；&gt；Kyle：发电机，对吗？
&gt;&gt; Kyle: Generators, right?
所以如果我有一堆不同的发电机都在运行
So what if I had a bunch of different generators that were all running in
不同的地方，他们彼此独立运行。
different places, and they were running independently with each other.
然后在某个时候两个发电机说嘿，
And then at some point two generators said hey,
我们需要相互协调。
we need to coordinate with each other.
所以让我们有一个沟通渠道，我们都可以互相阻挡，
So let's have a communication channel where we can both block each other,
两个都阻塞等待另一个出现。
both block waiting for the other one to show up.
一旦我们两个人都出现了，我们就可以发回一条信息
And as soon as both of us of showed up we can send a message back and
然后我们就可以回到独立的状态了。
then we can go back to being independent.
这确实是CSP的概念基础。
That's really the conceptual basis for CSP.
虽然这听起来非常复杂，但事实的确如此。
And while that sounds fantastically more complicated, it is.
它的威力也大得惊人。
It's also fantastically more powerful.
因为我们可以从字面上对应用程序的每个独立部分进行建模
Because we can literally model every independent piece of our application
完全独立于其他一切。
totally separate of everything else.
我们需要考虑的就是当我需要一条信息的时候，我会等待这条信息。
And all we have to think about is when I need a message I wait for the message.
或者当我需要发送消息时，我等待消息的发送。
Or when I need to send a message I wait for the sending of the message.
除此之外，我们没有理解或者
And other than that we have no understanding or
系统的任何其他部分的知识。
knowledge whatsoever of any of the other pieces of the system.
所以从理论上讲，实现可以采用这些小过程中的每一个
So theoretically the implementation could take each one of those little processes
然后把它们放在一个完全独立的线程上。
and put them on an entirely separate thread.
并且应用程序仍然以完全相同的方式工作。
And the application would still work exactly the same way.
这种并发模型，即并发的CSP模型，非常强大。
This model for concurrency, the CSP model for concurrency, is so powerful.
它是GO编程语言中的并发模型。
It is the model for concurrency in the Go programming language.
这也是Clojure和ClojureScript使用的。
It's also what Clojure and ClojureScript uses.
所以我不是，不仅仅是我编造了一些东西并且说它很酷。
So I'm not, it's not just me making something up and saying it's cool.
所以说真的
So really,
真的，超级聪明的人说这是做并发的方式。
really, really, super smart people have said this is the way to do concurrency.
在围棋中他们确实有线程，所以每一次围棋都被称为围棋例程，
And in Go they do have threads so every Go, it's called a Go routine,
每一个围棋例程最终都会在它自己的完全独立的线程上旋转起来。
every Go routine does end up spinning up on its own entirely independent thread.
这是围棋有如此高效率的神奇原因之一，所以
It's one of the magic reasons why Go has so much efficiency, so
很好的表现。
much performance to it.
因为我能够在我的应用程序中旋转所有这些不同的部分
Because I'm able to spin up all these different pieces of my application in
分开的线程。
separate threads.
但我有一种非常简单的方式在他们两人之间交流
But I have a really simple way of communicating between the two of them
通过封锁渠道，好吧。
through blocking channels, okay.
所以让我试着用代码来说明它看起来像什么。
So let me try to illustrate in code what that looks like.
我制作了一个频道，就像我在1号线上做的那样。
I make a channel like I do up here on line 1.
然后我有这个过程1，
And then I have this process1,
这是一个生成器，因为我们用JavaScript来表达它。
which is a generator cuz we're expressing this in terms of JavaScript.
他想通过频道发送一些东西，所以
He wants to send something down the channel, so
他使用一种叫做PUT的方法，他说这就是我想要发送它的频道。
he uses a method called put, and he says this is the channel I want to send it on.
所以我们通过通道是第一，而且
So we pass channel is the first, and
然后我们传递下一个参数是我们想要发送的消息。
then we pass the next argument is a message that we want to send.
您注意到我在PUT前面使用YOUTER，因为我想要
You notice I'm using yield in front of put, because I want for
要暂停的process1生成器。
the process1 generator to pause.
直到那个频道另一端的人说我准备好了
Until somebody on the other end of that channel says I'm ready to
记下这个信息。
take that message.
所以我说让步，
So I say yield put,
本地阻塞进程1，直到其他人出现并解除阻塞。
which locally blocks the process1 until somebody else comes along and unblocks it.
然后我在我的申请中有另一个过程，
Then I have this other process in my application,
也许在应用程序的一个完全不同的部分。
maybe in an entirely different part of the app.
他跑了，他说我需要一个来自频道的信息。
He's running along and he says I need a message from the ch channel.
所以他说我会屈服，就像我在10号线上做的那样。
So he says I'm gonna yield on a take, like I'm doing on line 10.
谁先到那里并不重要。&GT；&GT；Kyle：这就是它的酷之处。
It does not matter who gets there first. &gt;&gt; Kyle: That's what's cool about it.
我不必担心是否有消息在等着我。
I don't have to worry about whether or not there's a message waiting for me or not.
我只是说我想留个口信，我会等到一个准备好。
I just say I wanna take a message, and I'll wait until one's ready.
也许现在就准备好了，太好了。
Maybe it's ready right now, great.
如果不是，我就耐心等待。
If it's not, I'll just patiently wait.
我想推送一条信息。
I wanna push a message down.
我不需要知道某人是否准备好得到它。
I don't have to know whether or not somebody's ready to get it or not.
我只想等到有人准备好给我留言。
I'm just gonna wait until somebody's ready to take my message.
这就是让他们如此独立的原因。
That's what lets them be so independent.
因为这个通信通道的语义处理了这个问题
Because the semantics of this communication channel take care of that
沟通，背压，对我们来说。
communication, that back pressure, for us.
所以每当process2到了第10行，它说我准备好了，
So whenever process2 gets to line 10 and it says I'm ready to take it,
该消息立即通过通道传输。
immediately that message transfers through the channel.
并且进程2被解锁，
And process2 is unblocked,
并且进程1被解锁，然后他们就继续他们的一天。
and process1 is unblocked, and then they just go on about their day.
然后我们到了5号线，我们说等一下，
And then we get to line 5 and we say wait a minute,
我需要一个来自频道的信息。
I need a message from the channel.
所以我要再等一次。
So I'm gonna wait again.
然后过程2，他跑开了，嘿嘿说嘿，
And then process2, he's running along and hey says hey,
我要在频道上传递一个信息。
I've got a message to send on the channel.
所以我要等到有人准备好拿到它。
So I'm gonna wait until somebody's ready to get it.
然后他在频道上发回一条信息。
And he sends a message back up the channel.
然后进程1被解锁，然后进程2被解锁，
And then process1 is unblocked, and then process2 is unblocked,
他们继续他们的一天。
and they go on about their day.
所以你可以有几百行完全独立的代码
So you can have hundreds of lines of totally independent code that
不需要担心系统的任何其他部分。
doesn't have to worry about any other piece of the system.
唯一需要担心的是当你知道
And the only part that has to worry about it is when you know
我有一个频道，我需要一些数据，或者
I've got a channel that I need some data on, or
我有一个通道，我需要推送一些数据。
I've got a channel that I need to push some data along.
我只想等着有人告诉我这没什么。
I'm just gonna wait for somebody to tell me that's okay.
在这个抽象的掩盖之下，CSP范例是什么
And underneath the covers this abstraction, the CSP paradigm is what
为您管理所有的复杂性。&GT；&GT；Kyle：好的，
manages all that complexity for you. &gt;&gt; Kyle: Okay,
现在围棋和Clojure中非常聪明的人，
now the really, really smart folks in Go, and Clojure,
和ClojureScript，他们非常确信这是
and ClojureScript, they're pretty convinced this is the most
到目前为止发明的用于并发管理的强大模型。
powerful model invented to date for concurrency management.
我也不是一个反对他们的人，我认为他们是对的。
And I'm not one to bet against them, I think they're right.
我确实认为这是我见过的最强大的模式
I do think this is the most powerful pattern that I've ever seen or
听到任何人谈论并发管理。
heard anybody talk about for concurrency management.
顺便说一下，我对它很着迷。
I'm fascinated by it, by the way.
我花了一年的时间研究如何更深入地理解这一点
I've spent the last year researching how to understand this deeper and
查看将其应用于我的用户界面的实际方法。
seeing practical ways of applying it to my user interfaces.
我已经花了一年的时间，我仍然觉得我几乎没有抓伤
And I've spent a year at it and I still feel like I'm barely scratching
与这些聪明人相比。
the surface compared to these smart people.
整个站在巨人的肩膀上，我就像是执着于
That whole standing on the shoulders of giants, I'm like clinging on for
亲爱的生命。
dear life.
他们知道的东西我几乎都不知道。
I don't even hardly know the stuff that they know.
但我相信这里有很多我们甚至没有的东西
But I'm convinced that there is a whole lot here that we haven't even
真正揭开了真相，划破了表面。
really uncovered and scratched the surface with.
所以ClojureScript，维护ClojureScript的人，特别是一个叫
So ClojureScript, guys that maintain ClojureScript, specifically a guy named
David Swanadet，我很抱歉David Nolan，他在Twitter上叫Swanadet。
David Swanadet, I'm sorry David Nolan who goes by Swanadet on Twitter.
超级聪明的家伙，每次我听到他说话我都会想我是怎么做到的，
Super brilliant guy, every time I hear him talk I'm just like how did I even,
他只是放弃了这个知识，就像它很容易，而我学到了很多东西。
he just drops down this knowledge like it's so easy and I'm learning so much.
但是他有一个叫做Om，O-M的UI框架。
But he's got a UI framework called Om, O-M.
及其ClojureScript，ClojureScript被移植到Java，
And its ClojureScript, which ClojureScript is ported to Java,
它的ClojureScript是Clojure，可以在浏览器中以JavaScript运行。
it's ClojureScript is Clojure that can run in JavaScript in the browser.
他们到处使用这种CSP，
And they use this CSP all over the place,
它在CSP中对整个用户界面进行建模。
it models the entire user interface in CSP.
他制作了这个，最令人惊叹的
And he produces this, the most amazing and
我见过的性能最好的用户界面。
most performant user interface I've ever seen.
太不可思议了。
It's incredible.
所以我相信有很多
So I'm convinced that there's a whole lot of,
我们还没有触及到它的能力的皮毛。
we haven't scratched the surface of the capabilities of it.
这就是为什么我试图说服人们也考虑这一点。
And that's why I'm trying to convince people to think about this as well.
这是另一个开始围绕我们的应用程序建模的工具。
This is another one of those tools to start to model our applications around.